We're busy making this very exciting soccer scoring game, and we have got the basics of our two little
turtles and the outline of our field in place.
Now, what we want to do is we want to start kicking the ball.
Now what we're going to have a look at in this next section is defining the kick function for kicking
the ball.
But it's not going to do anything.
Remember we talked about this earlier that what functions do is they perform something.
They're a black box that is doing something that is returning a value.
So at the moment this function as we're creating it says the box now is not going to do something.
It's going to do something later when we use the kick function.
So we're going to work through what the kick function is doing.
We won't see anything happening on the screen yet, but you will see something happening later when
we need to start kicking that ball.
You can see here we have defined kick, and before I mentioned that some functions do not need parameters
and this is one of them because I don't need to pass anything to the function, I just want it to do
something inside.
So we have defined this function called kick okay.
So what we ultimately want this function to do is we want the ball to move towards the goal, but of
course we don't want the ball moving to the same place every time.
We want it to be random.
We don't want the goalie to know where the ball is going to go.
So in order to do that, we need a little bit more complex things.
But we have looked at all of this and you should easily understand it.
The first thing we do over here is set the heading.
So we've set the heading to 180.
And if you remember from above, 180 is west because we want the ball to go west towards our goals.
We then have this variable here called angle, which we want to store a random integer between and including
zero and 27.
So after a few trials, I figured out that this was the exact size of the goals, and I didn't want
the ball to go further than the goals or below the goals.
But you could change this.
So say I decided I actually wanted to make this 50.
Basically all that's going to do is now your ball can go even further towards the top of the screen
and even lower towards the bottom of the screen.
So changing that.
Well, try and change it and see what happens, and you'll see how the ball can reach further parts.
But for now we're just going to keep it at 27.
But we want it to be a random angle between these numbers.
Our next variable we have here is direction.
And again we want a random number.
And we want that random number to be either 0 or 1.
And you'll see where we use this below here.
So this direction variable, what we want it to actually do is we've put it inside an if statement.
So if direction is zero, if that was chosen as the random number, we want the ball to go left by that
random angle.
So if you think about it, what's happening is let's say the random number here for direction was zero.
The random angle was ten.
This ball dot left function is going to turn the ball left by ten degrees, which was our angle over
here.
So that's what this will do.
Else if the direction isn't zero.
So in other words, if it is one, then we want the ball to turn right by that random angle which we
will which randomly was ten degrees for this example.
So you'll see when the program runs, the ball is constantly moving in a random position.
Now if we didn't have the left and right, then what would happen is every time the program runs and
a random angle is chosen, the ball is always just going to go up because it's always just going to
turn right, right, right.
But we don't want that.
We want it to go left as well.
So we need it to go either way left and right.
Okay.
So the next line we have here is just moving the ball forward towards the goal.
So I've also worked out that the optimal number for that is 320 pixels.
But we could change that to further just means the ball's going to end up further down here on the screen.
Let me actually run it so you can see.
Positioning.
Remember it's not going to change for last time.
But what I've done is I want to win.
This ball is kicked.
I want it to end up somewhere along here where our goals will be.
If we made this more, let's say 350, the ball's going to end up more down here.
Okay.
We then have this if statement over here.
And what this does is we basically want to know if the goalie has saved the ball or not.
So you might just think, well, maybe you would think surely if the position of the ball is in the
same position as the goalie, then the ball has been saved.
The reason I haven't said that if the goalie position is equal to the position of the ball, then the
ball is saved is because for the position of the goalie and for the position of the ball to be in the
exact same place is very unlikely.
Because think about it, it's a huge screen.
It could easily be off by one pixel and it might look like it's saved, but in fact it's not exactly
there.
So instead of saying that, we've rather said that if the distance between the goalie and the ball is
less than 35, then it is a save.
Else it is a goal.
So you could also change this.
If I made this bigger, say 100, then the goalie can be even further away for the from the ball for
it to be a save.
But I've kind of worked out that 35 is a good number for this.
Okay.
Then down here we just are halving the total over here.
Because what I want to happen is I want the ball to go back to the center of the screen over here once
it's been kicked, but I don't want the user or the player to see the ball traveling back here.
So I've hidden this turtle and it has just gone back to the center.
And once it is back at the center, it is reshown.
And basically this statement over here brings it back to the middle of the screen.
So yeah, that's basically what this function is doing.
We're going to run it for you later.
So you can see exactly how all of these different components come into play.